hello guys and welcome back to this video and this one we are going to install nltk and we are going
to see how we can use the nltk features such as the stemmer limitizer and all this kind of stuff
first of all nltk is a leading platform for by the building by some programs to work with the
human language it is you it is widely used for initial language processing and it has
a strong large corpora and lexical resources resources such as world net which we are going
to use later in this tutorial for limitizing and basically you cannot work in natural language
processing field without knowing about nltk so first of all we need to install it using
bep install nltk so inside your terminal we're going to initiate the command bep install nltk
and of course because i have it here already it's going to tell me that it's already satisfied
and don't forget that you can apply this basically by having an explanation mark and
applying vip install nltk it have the same it will have the same result actually because
uh this is basically is the same as applying it to your terminal
so after installing nltk you need to install some corpora for example uh some data that it doesn't
come pre-installed with nltk because it has a large size so if you need instead if you need any
additional data on your nltk you have to start the nltk and then start nltk downloader so after
installing nltk you can initialize a python terminal inside your terminal or even inside your notebook and
then we're going to import nltk so we're going to import nltk so this line runs successfully so that's
mean that nltk is already installed and everything's fine so you can initialize the command nltk dot download
which is basically going to initialize some gui for you that you can install from it all the
packages that have in nltk you can see here this is the collections these are the corpora and these
are the models and all these are all the packages you can basically go here and install all the
packages if you have the enough space and you're going to deal with nltk for a large time and instead
you can just go through the corporate and install the corporate that you want the corporate that we're
going to need is wordnet so make sure you have wordnet installed and uh here we're going to
install it and of course it tells me that the package wordnet is up to date because i already
downloaded it so that's how you install ntk and its data so uh you have all of these documented here in
this notebook so if you needed to go back to it anytime you'll find it documented here
so let's get started first by import nltk in our notebook and have some text here the text here please
notice that the text here have wasn't which was which has a comma here and we're going to deal with
tokenizers first let's see the normal tokenizer the regix tokenizer that we have built before which was
surpassing uh the split function of the string and you can see here that we have wasn't as a single word
in some cases we need to interpret wasn't as two different words was and not because basically wasn't
and was uh we were treated differently but we need to have woes and not because then we can deal with
negation and we know that this woes is uh negated by the not so uh let's take a look at the tokenizer
of the nltk we have nltk dot wood tokenize so let's see the output of it and you can see here that
woes and not are separated woes and not are different tokens and this can be very useful in some cases so
first we have a word tokenizer that is better than the normal tokenizer and of course you can see here
that the empty set is not included in the words so you only have tokens that are actual tokens and not
empty space now into stemming to apply stemming there are multiple algorithms for stemming in ltk
and in general the portrait steamer is the steamer that we have talked about in the previous tutorial
which basically applies some rules like you're moving some additional characters and you're using
some different characters so the rules for portrait simmer can be found here uh it is all documented in the
nltk because it's an open source library so you can find all the code um and you can go through it
simply so to use the portrait simmer we're going to import the portrait simmer from nltk.stem and we're
going to initialize an object just some object here we have some words some plural words and we're going
to see what the steamer is going to apply to them and you can see here this is this is a different way
of defining strings when you have some variables and you need to include these variables inside the
string you just use an f in front of your string and this is basically means that this string is going
to be a formatted string and by having career places we're going to define variables inside the
string and these variables are going to call the variables themselves here so here we're going to
have word and uh this another character places we have going to have the steamer dot stem which is the
function that basically stem our string and we're going to pass the word so applying this still we're going to
have each word and each its corresponding stem so you can see here that it indeed apply the rule
which which basically was saying that if we have ses we're going to reduce it into a single s and we
have ies we reduce it into i and all these kind of rules that we have talked we we have looked into
these rules in the previous tutorial and you can double check it here in this so that's how you use the
the stemmer the porter stemmer there is another stemmer that is called the snowboard snowball stemmer
one of the advantages of snowball uh stemmer over the portrait stemmer is that it supports different
languages and you can check the languages that the snowboard stemmer support using the snowboard
stemmer the languages and you can see here it has arabic danish jewish english uh french german italian all
these kind of languages you can use and you can see it has the porter stemmer which is basically an
english stemmer which is this stemmer so let's initialize our stemmer we're going to initialize
it and we need to pass the language that we're going to be using and indeed it's going to be the english so
here we have the sn stemmer so let's apply the cell and let's take a look at the uh the output of these
cells basically most of the time the snowball stemmer and the porter stemmer have similar results but in some
cases the snowball stemmer um is better in most of the cases the snowball stemmer will be better let's
take a look at this one we have here the sn stemmer and we're going to stem the generously word take a
look at the stem it's generous what about the stemmer the portrait stemmer if we use the portrait
stemmer we're going to have it into a general because it's going to just remove all these uh text
so snowball stemmer and portrait stemmer are similar similar but the snowball stemmer most of the time have
better results so it might be better to go into snowball stemmer um most of the time so into
limitizing and as we said in the previous tutorial limitizing is about reducing the word into its root
to do so we have to have a like a tree bank or a knowledge bank that have all the word and words and
its roots and this is called the wordnet so here we have wordnet limitizer in ltk um that's why we installed and
download the wordnet the wordnet corpora from the ltk download so initialize the wordnet limitizer
using a wordnet limitizer class and let's take a look at the uh limitization of all the plurus words
that we have defined um here and let's take a look at this and flies have been reduced into fly dies have been
reduced into die and um this might be a little bit weird but this is the root as limitizing seeds and
uh you can see here not all the cases are good but most of the case not all the cases are good but uh
each anywhere that it has already root for it it will be reduced into a web so in summary what we have
done in this tutorial we have downloaded and installed nltk and we also know how to download nltk data
we now know how to use the nltk tokenizer and how it is better than the regix tokenizer we know how we
now know how to deal with nltk stemmers how to stem words both in portrait stemmer and snowball
stemmer and also in different languages because we have different languages in the snowball stemmer we
know also how to use the wordnet limitizer from uh nltk so that's it for this video in the next video we're
going to deal with different kind of features for our text specifically the the boss tags and the
parsing tree and we're going to see how we can apply these into our text so see you guys in the next one